<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Newes from Antvverp, the .10. day of August. 1580 Contayning, a speciall view of the present affayres of the lowe countreyes: revuealed and brought to lyght, by sundrie late intercepted letters, of certaine vizarded and counterfeyt countrey men of the same countreyes. Translated into English, partly out of French, and partly out of Lattin: according to the originall copie, printed at Antwerp, by William Riuiere, a sworne printer, and bookseller.</title>
            <title>Afgheworpene brieven van sommighe ... valsche patriotten. English</title>
            <author>Fredericke, abbot of Marolles.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1580</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B11202</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 692</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112793</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848036</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848036</idno>
            <idno type="VID">176474</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B11202)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176474)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 236:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Newes from Antvverp, the .10. day of August. 1580 Contayning, a speciall view of the present affayres of the lowe countreyes: revuealed and brought to lyght, by sundrie late intercepted letters, of certaine vizarded and counterfeyt countrey men of the same countreyes. Translated into English, partly out of French, and partly out of Lattin: according to the originall copie, printed at Antwerp, by William Riuiere, a sworne printer, and bookseller.</title>
                  <title>Afgheworpene brieven van sommighe ... valsche patriotten. English</title>
                  <author>Fredericke, abbot of Marolles.</author>
                  <author>Schetz, Gaspar, d. 1580.</author>
                  <author>Georg, von Schönenberg, Bishop of Worms, 1530-1595.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[36] p. : 4#20.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Charlewood,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1580]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Letters by Fredericke, abbot of Marolles, Gaspar Schetz, and Lord Wormes [i.e. Georg von Schönenberg, Bishop of Worms, 1530-1595]. A translation of "Afgheworpene brieuen van sommighe .. valsche patriotten".</note>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Intercepted letters.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴ E² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of independence, 1556-1648.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176474:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176474:1"/>
            <p>Newes from Antvverp, the .10. day of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> 1580.</p>
            <p>Contayning, A ſpeciall view of the preſent affayres of the lowe Countreyes:</p>
            <p>Reuealed and brought to lyght, by ſundrie late inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted Letters, of certaine vizarded and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeyt Countreymen of the ſame Countreyes.</p>
            <p>¶ Tranſlated into Engliſh, partly out of French, and partly out of Lattin: According to the originall Copie, printed at Antwerp, by William Riuiere, a ſworne Printer, and Bookſeller.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device? (not found in McKerrow): thistle flower</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London, by <hi>John Charlewood.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:176474:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176474:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll perſons bearing affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to the Common wealth of theſe Countreyes, deſire to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged of the oppreſsions, which the warre of neceſſity leadeth and bringeth with it. But this deſire is onely a generall diſcourſe. For the effects of the ſame are hindred ſtyll, and heretofore haue bene interrupted by an irreſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which happeneth not (as many haue thought,) by the faulte of the cheefe Captaynes and Gouernours, who, haue ſo often, bothe by woord of mouth, and wrytinges in print declared, what counſell was meete to be taken, and with ſo great paynes and dillygence ſent into all the Prouinces, yea, and tranſported themſelues thyther in their proper perſons.</p>
            <p>But the fault thereof is to be imputed to the particular Commynalties, the greateſt parte whereof doo order their matter with extreme delayes. The cauſes of ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes are diuerſe. But the principall of the ſame is, that ſome ſubtyll and wylie fellowes amongſt vs, of the ſame humour that theſe were of (whoſe Letters thou ſhalt ſee heere.) When they counterfeyted the good Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymen with vs, doo feede vs with a vayne hope of peace, eyther by the way of Spayne, or Almayne, or by ſome other meanes? Hoping, that as already vnder coulour of peace, they haue deuided the prouinces of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toys,
<pb facs="tcp:176474:3"/> and Haynault from vs: ſo they will bring the lyke to paſſe amongſt the other Prouinces, that are yet at vnitie. But if thoſe thinges which we learne by the confeſſion of our enemies, ought to be taken for a trueth: thou ſhalt know freendly Reader, by theſe Letters, that we may not any longer looke for peace with the king of Spayne, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we will yet ſuffer our ſelues to be burnt. And therfore it remayneth that we make good prouiſion to defend our ſelues valiauntly by all meanes poſſyble, yea, to repulſe the force that we ſee repayring for our ruine: Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, if the Spaniardes obtayne the kingdome of Portugall. Which God forbyd.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:176474:3"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Copies of Letters of the Abbot of Marolles to the Cardinall Granuellan. The firſt Letter.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Lord, within theſe fowre</hi> laſt moneths, I haue written many Letters to your moſt honorable &amp; reuerend Lordſhyp, the which I feare by reaſon of the great daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of the wayes, are not ſo ſoone come to your hands as I would wiſh. Becauſe I haue receyued no aunſwer, but to thoſe of the .xxviij. of Ianuary. I would not let ſlyp the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion therof, for the vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of the trueth therof, finding ſo<note n="1" place="margin">Not too ſure for he was take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> ſure a man as the Lord of <hi>Grobbendonk,</hi> ſendeth into thoſe parties, for his perticular affayres: to write this alſo, and to ſend therwith the copie of the laſt Letter written the xvij. of this moneth: whereby your Lordſhip ſhall ſée the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of my wryting from time to time, to this ende, that in caſe I may vnderſtand the none receypt of my ſayde for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Letters: I might<note n="2" place="margin">The Abbot thinkes, that the Cardinal kepeth a Regiſter of his Letters becauſe they are of ſo great ſubſtaunce, learning and elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. But he taketh not ſo much paynes as to reade them, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wen out of the Abbot, the thing he preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note> alſo ſend after the Copies. Sithence my ſayd laſt Letters we haue receyued, vnderſtanding with great gréefe &amp; meruayle, the departing of the Lord of <hi>Auſsi,</hi> from my Lord the Prince of <hi>Parma,</hi> to goe and reioyne him ſelfe to the Prince of <hi>Orenge:</hi> Delyuering into his handes withall, his Caſtell of <hi>Liekerk lez Aloſte.</hi> Alſo the deteining of the Colonell <hi>De heze,</hi> and other partakers, whome my Lordes of <hi>Riſbourge</hi> and <hi>Mountigny</hi> haue layde holde on: laying to their charge, that they would haue wrought ſome treaſon, or ſlippery pranck to the Campe, lying before <hi>Tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nay,</hi> and that by the intelligence and ſubornation of the ſayd Prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> they ſhould haue ſpoyled the principall heades of our ſayd<note n="3" place="margin">The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe of Riſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourge &amp; Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigny, accuſed him of an other matter, to wyt, that he had intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygence with the Duke of Amon.</note> Campe, and brought them by force to <hi>Tournay</hi> aforeſayd, to the ende to haue ſunke our Army af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward. I am ſo much aſtoniſhed, that I knowe not what to ſay, ſéeing<note n="4" place="margin">You ſhall ſee an other manner of one: when the Conſpiracies of the Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes with the Spaniards ſhall be diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> this wickedneſſe &amp; lyghtneſſe, which I feare much, will greatly diminiſh all our credites with his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, (who I doubt not) will be highly offended therwith, and
<pb facs="tcp:176474:4"/> alſo augment his diſtruſt, although the<note n="5" place="margin">Such as thou haſt bene.</note> ſtedfaſt ſetled, and well reſolued ſort, ought not to ſuffer any thing therfore.</p>
            <p>I remember that I haue by diuers Letters repreſented like inconueniences to your moſt honorable Lordſhip, knowing the ſleyghts and wyles of the ſayde Prince, being ſo<note n="6" place="margin">Yet, thou thoughteſt to be a more crafty Foxe, when thou diddeſt counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine with thy complices in the counſel of eſtate. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder ſhadowe of thy Ambaſſadorſhip, thou madeſt thy boaſts with thy complices, to make him fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the trap with, all the good cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymen, ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, thoſe of the Religion. But God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued them.</note> ſubtill and ſuch a Foxe, and the inconſtancy, &amp; couetouſneſſe of ſome in the world: <hi>Quos merito leues iudicare poteram habentes etiam</hi>
               <note n="7" place="margin">Wytneſſes the foure thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Duckats of Pencion, that the Duke of <hi>Terra noua,</hi> hath promiſed thee.</note> 
               <hi>animam venalem.</hi> Wherevnto great héede is to be taken. For they haue, <hi>A dextris et a ſinistris,</hi> great Factors, to wyt, the<note n="8" place="margin">Wherfore then dooſt thou ſpread a rumor that he hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence with the Pope, and the King of Spayne.</note> Duke of <hi>Alanſon,</hi> &amp; the ſayd Prince, who accorde toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in nothing, but in making ſharp warre againſt the king of Spayne our Lord &amp; Maiſter, to ſtrippe him of that is his. Howbeit, the ouerthrowe of the Lord <hi>de La noue,</hi> lately hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in Flaunders, and the victorie now newly wonne in Frizeland, vppon the ſayd Prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> his men ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoring to hinder the ſuccors of <hi>Groeninghen,</hi> will giue great impediment to their deſſeins and purpoſes in this behalfe.</p>
            <p>My Lord, I will pray the Creator to giue vnto your moſt honorable and reuerend Lordſhip, a long &amp; happy lyfe, after I haue ſaluted the good graces of the ſame, with my moſt humble recommendations. Beſéeching your Lordſhip, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, that the ſame would vouchſafe to preſent to his Maieſtie my Letters comming with theſe. Wherby I ſend vnto the ſame, the continuance of my good wyll, and what hath paſſed touching my matter, the which I deſire to be conſtrued in good part.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From <hi>Cullen,</hi> 
                  <date>the .xxv. of Iune. <hi>1580.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline> Vnder was written.
<signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt honorable and reuerend Lordshippes, moſt humble and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient Oratour. <hi>Fredericke,</hi> Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot of <hi>Marolles.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer type="direction"> 
               <hi>The ſuperſcription was thus.</hi>
               <lb/> To my Lord. My Lord the moſt <hi>hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and reuerend Cardinall</hi> Granuellan, &amp;c. my most honorable Lord.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:176474:4"/>
            <head>¶ To the Cardinall <hi>Granuellan.</hi> The ſecond Letter.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Lord, although by my three former</hi> Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters laſt ſent to your moſt honorable, &amp; reuerend Lordſhip, the one of the firſt, the other of the .xij. of Aprill, and the laſt of the .x. of May, (which I think are ſurely conueyed by the meanes of my Lord, the Duke of <hi>Terra Noua</hi>) I had ſufficiently informed your honourable Lordſhyp, in what ſtate the affayres ſtande in theſe parties, yet would I not fayle in my dutie, to ſende vnto the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine at this preſent, what hath paſſed: Albeit, that ſince my laſt Letters, there hath not happened any great chaunge, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the good victorie that God hath giuen to the Marqueſſe of <hi>Risbourg,</hi> acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panied with the <hi>Albanoys</hi> &amp; <hi>Wallons,</hi> who haue ſurpriſed, ouerthrowen, put to flight and diſperſed the Prince of <hi>Orenges</hi> men being in Flau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders, vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leading &amp; gouernment of <hi>Mounſier de La noue,</hi> a Frenchman, who with many of his men, was taken priſoner. The which in good ſothe, is a very good gyrde giuen to the enimie, and will coole his corage from enterpriſing hereafter according to his former cuſtome. I vnderſtand that a part of the glory of this victory may well be attributed to the ſayd <hi>Albanoys,</hi> who by report played the men moſt valiauntly.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding this, we vnderſtand from <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> that they doo not<note n="1" place="margin">They haue well ſhewed it vnto you, when they haue taken two Townes by force, and cutte in peeces your olde company of blood.</note> greatly quayle at this ouerthrowe, but with all furie prepare them ſelues to gather together theyr ſpoyled and diſperſed men, and to make a new leuie. Yea, and that they labour very dilligently in their eſtates. <hi>De ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negando rege, et de transferendo imperio.</hi> As touching the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of renouncing his Maieſty, and declaring him to be fallen from his Ryghtes: I vnderſtand they haue already<note n="2" place="margin">Thou thy ſelfe haſt bene a hundred tymes of this opinion.</note> reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vppon it, hauing taken a ſhewe and cullour vppon the perſon of the Duke of <hi>Alanſon</hi> whome they fayne, that they will adopt, giuing to vnderſtand to the ſimple and vnwyſe
<pb facs="tcp:176474:5"/> ſort, that the aſſumption of the ſayd Lord Duke, would cauſe a warre againſt the Crowne of Fraunce. Preſuppoſing that the moſt Chriſtian King his brother (giuing vnto him fauour and ſupport) would bende his forces vpon <hi>Italy, Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy, Haynault,</hi> and <hi>Artoys.</hi> And that by meanes thereof, the warres would be turned out of <hi>Flaunders, Brabant,</hi> and other Prouinces that will not be reconcyled. But knowing the ſubtylties and wyles of ſuch as at this day are in credite amongſt their Eſtates: I haue alwayes perſwaded my ſelfe, that they will<note n="3" place="margin">The Monke thinketh y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euerie man ſo dallyeth with Princes, as he hath done, denying thryſe his Waye: and ſelling his fayth and honour, for the Abbay of S. Bartin, or a pencion in ſteede therof.</note> ſet the ſayde Duke in the féelde onely for a ſhadowe, that couering them ſelues with his cloake, they may the more eaſily attayne to theyr pretended, and deſired renunciation. Which obtayned,<note n="4" place="margin">My Lord the Abbot ſhall not be called to this counſell.</note> (vſing an other ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geme) they will bring into conſideration, and delyberation, whether his perſon wyll be beneficiall, and profitable for the Countrey.</p>
            <p>Not forgetting to ſette the pride and<note n="5" place="margin">Is there any greater lyghtnes and inconſtancie, then in my Lord the Abbot, and his complices?</note> lyghtneſſe of the Frenchmen as a counterweight, againſt the crueltie of the Spaniardes. The ſmall meanes and habillytie that he hath to ſuccour the Countreyes, for aſmuch as the Crowne is not fallen vnto him: and when he commeth to the ſame, that hée wyll be too mightie a King, and too néere a neyghbour: and that ſo he might eaſily degenerate into tyranny, (whereof they call them ſelues great enemies, although by theyr<note n="6" place="margin">Theſe abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable actes be, that they take heede that they be not betrayed and ſolde by theſe Gentlemen Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bots, who accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoming to ſell their God in the Maſſe, make no ſcruple to ſell men to eſtabliſhe their kettell.</note> ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable actes, a man might iudge them tyranny it ſelfe.) Therefore that it is in no wyſe, to be counſelled to accept him for theyr King: They may alſo ſet in concurrence, to make a fayre ſhew of the matter, the Emperour, the Quéene of Englande, and certayne other Princes neyghbours, not forgetting (though he come laſt) the Prince of <hi>Orenge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then comming to the<note n="7" place="margin">This Monke iudgeth all at his pleaſure, of all the Princes of Chriſtendome: as though he were our holy Father, and that he were theyr Scholemaiſter.</note> eſtimation of the merites of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them, the Emperour wyll be found too weake, and too young, yea, ſuſpected becauſe he is a Catholique, and of the houſe of <hi>Auſtriche.</hi> The Quéene of England ſcant capable, for that ſhe is a Woman, and other Princes in no wyſe to be lyked of. But hauing regard to the long experience of the Prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> to the great and honorable ſeruices by
<pb facs="tcp:176474:5"/> him done, for the recouering of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> liberty of the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, the reſtoring of the Priuiledges: By reaſon whereof, he hath bene baniſhed, depriued of his Eſtates, honors, and goods. Yea, they will not forget to place amongſt his firſt quarters, and for the fayreſt parte of his Armes, that he hath<note n="8" place="margin">This is as great an honour as can be.</note> brought in and maynteyned, the<note n="9" place="margin">In deede it is new to the eares of theſe Aſſes and Coltes, that neuer heard the voyce of the Goſpell.</note> new Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whereof they are ſo deſirous, and farre in loue with all. That therfore of due deſart, he ought to be choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, elected, and accepted for King, giuing reaſonable contentation to the others. The which I ſée verie likely to come to paſſe. If it be ſo: his Maieſty ſhall thereby loſe but the name a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, <hi>Ad tempus:</hi> For the Prince in effect is the ſame already. As for me, I ſay the ſame, that I haue ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> repeated by my former Letters, that to haue peace, it is<note n="10" place="margin">To deceyue them.</note> expedient to haue more: or to make better warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, then hath bene made hytherto. Otherwiſe, one whyle they will be beaten: an other whyle they will beate. As we fall out by the ouerthrowe aboueſayd. And a lyttle after by the reconquering of <hi>Dieſt,</hi> and <hi>Malines</hi> before. They of <hi>Cambray, Tournay,</hi> and <hi>Bonchaim,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue theyr excurſions vpon theyr neyghbours, deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Countrey, ſo that euery where is nothing to be ſéen but<note n="11" place="margin">This could not be ſeene without the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the heads and Magiſtrates of Artoys &amp; Haynault, who haue perſwaded the poore people, that they would graunt them peace, and in the meane while haue plunged them in the whyrle pytte of all the myſeries of the warre, not regarding any other thing, ſauing to gayne credite or recompence of the Spaniardes, and theyr miniſters, with the whole ruyne of the people.</note> myſerie and pouertie. And it ſhould be a godly déede to take héed aforeha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, to other infinit euils y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vs. As touching the laſt Letters, that it pleaſed your honorable Lordſhip to wryte vnto me: I made my aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the x. of May: And amongſt other thinges, ſhewed vnto the ſame my complaynt and gréefe, that the Letter therin mencioned, which it had pleaſed his Maieſtie to write vnto me, was not delyuered to my hands: And am conſtrayned to doo the lyke againe, for that I cannot yet recouer the ſame. Wherfore I am in extreme ſorrow, for that I knowe not the contentes of it, nor can not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my ſelfe according to the ſame. Notwithſtanding, I haue receiued a Letter of the .xx. of the moneth paſt, from my Lord, the Prince of <hi>Parma.</hi> Whereby he aduertiſed me, that his Maieſtie had named me of his counſell of
<pb facs="tcp:176474:6"/> Eſtate. And that I ſhould returne into <hi>Haynault,</hi> to be aſſyſtant in the ſayde Counſell in proper perſon. I haue aunſwered his excellencie, that I will not fayle to obey his commaundement, to employ my ſelfe with heart and affection, to the ſeruing of ſo principall a charge. But that by reaſon of the ſickneſſe of my Lady, the Ducheſſe of <hi>Arſchot:</hi> my Lord the Duke her huſband could not ſo ſoone depart. Who hath often required me not to forſake him, but to ſtaye for his going to reenter into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey together. Whervnto his ſayd excellencie, for<note n="12" place="margin">To haue two at once.</note> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne good reſpects hath condiſcended. And I wyll not fayle to worke all manner of forwardneſſe at our ſayde returne, to procure in good earneſt, with all ſincerity and fidelitie the reſtabliſhing of the affayres. And although I haue vnderſtoode, that touching the denomination of my Lord the Prelate of Saint <hi>Gertrude</hi> and me, there hath priuily bene moued ſome diffycultie: Specially, by certayne<note n="13" place="margin">One Traytor kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth another very wel.</note> Eccleſiaſticall perſons, ſuſpecting, or wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully quarrelling at our former actions, yet will not we therefore leaue of to mayntaine our ſelues in the order and degrée, wherein it hath pleaſed his Maieſtie to ſette vs for the feruent deſire we haue to do ſeruice to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, as good and better then they, &amp; that we will not yéeld or giue place to ſuch perſons, ielous of our proſperitie. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our behauiours ſhalbe ſuch as God, his Maieſtie, the Countrey, Cobrethren, &amp; others ſhall receyue accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſeruice therby. In this behalfe, my Lord, I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend my ſelfe, to your moſt honourable &amp; reuerend Lordſhips good grace, praying y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may pleaſe the ſame to make me partaker of his maieſties good grace. Whervn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to to my great gréefe, I cannot write, for that hytherto I could not recouer his Letters. Wherfore I deſire to be excuſed.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From <hi>Cullen,</hi> 
                  <date>this .xvij. of Iune. 1580.</date>
               </dateline> Vnder was written.
<signed>Your moſt honorable and reuerende Lordships, moſt humble Oratour.</signed> And ſigned.
<signed>
                  <hi>Fredericke</hi> Abbot of <hi>Marolles.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:176474:6"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A Copie of the Letters of the Abbot of Marolles, to the King. The thirde Letter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Soueraygne Lorde.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas I haue by diuers Letters, giuen</hi> aduertiſement to your Maieſtie, that I deſyred nothing more, then to haue the meane to yéelde all manner of obedience, and doo moſt humble ſeruice to the ſame in whatſoeuer it ſhould vouchſafe to commaund me: As being of a moſt prompt and ready will to render my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyfull endeuour of fidelity and naturallitie. Beſides that, I haue alſo giuen a more perticular accoumpt of my good<note n="1" place="margin">That is to ſay, of my treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. For being Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> States. I would with others lyke vnto me, haue enducet them vnder coulour of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> peace, to haue letten the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues to haue bene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued.</note> intencions, to my Lorde the Duke of <hi>Terra Noua,</hi> being in this Cittie of <hi>Cullen,</hi> who at his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had aſſured me, that your Maieſtie ſhould be aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed thereof, to giue me vnderſtanding of the noble plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the ſame. Yet notwithſtanding I haue not hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, to my vnſpeakeable gréefe, bene honoured with any<note n="2" place="margin">The Spaniards looue treaſon, but no traytors.</note> commaundementes by Letter, nor otherwyſe.</p>
            <p>By meanes whereof, I am, and haue bene in great perplexitie, hauing ſtayed in this Cittie<note n="3" place="margin">You mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſay your Mattins, &amp; ſing Maſſe euery day.</note> ydle, ſince the departing of the ſayde Lord,<note n="4" place="margin">Why go you not then to rule your Monkes, who will finde you e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to doo? But my Lord Abbot rather med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth with matters of Eſtate, and of the Court then to feede his Hogs, <hi>Secundum illud ne Clerici ſe immiſceant negotijs ſecularibus.</hi>
               </note> For that I knewe not whereabout to employ my ſelfe, for want of charge or commiſſion. Howbeit, the twenty of the moneth paſt, I receyued Letters from my Lord the Prince of <hi>Parma:</hi> whereby he aduertiſed me, that it had pleaſed your Maieſtie, to name me of his Counſell of<note n="5" place="margin">It muſt needes be that the Eſtate is well gouerned, for that froc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Monkes gouerne the ſame according to the olde prouerbe. Since decrees had wings, and Sergeantes carryed Mayles, and Monkes went a horſeback: The world had nothing but all euyll.</note> Eſtate. And that I ſhould tranſport my ſelfe immediatly into <hi>Haynault,</hi> to aſſyſte there in my proper perſon.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176474:7"/>
            <p>Wherat I reioyced greatly, vnderſtanding that<note n="6" place="margin">His Maieſtie is ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunt of it. But the Prince of Parma, vpon his blankes aſſigned, wryteth what he liſteth.</note> your Maieſtie had not forgotten his ſo humble a<note n="7" place="margin">Chaplen &amp; Oratour for the care he hath of his Chappel, and to ſay continuall prayers.</note> Chaplen and Orator, wholy dedicated to his ſeruice, honouring him with ſo principall an Eſtate. For which I moſt humbly thanke the ſame: aſſuring your Maieſtie that I wyll not fayle, according to my dutifull power, with all<note n="8" place="margin">Such as thou haſt yeelded to Don Iohn, and ſince to my Lord the Duke of Aniou, &amp; laſtly to my Lord the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke. Whoſe Almonens thou haſt bene, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken them all three.</note> fidelytie and integritie, to doo my dutie in the ſame charge. And wyll procure the<note n="9" place="margin">My Lord Abbot, we wyll take heede of you, and ſuch as you are.</note> reducing of the Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Citties, Commonalties, and particuler perſonnes, with all my poſſibillytie, that all thinges maye in ſhort tyme be<note n="10" place="margin">It ſhould be better for my Lord Abbot to reduce him ſelfe and his Monkes, to ſome good order and diſcipline.</note> ſette agayne in good order: for the better or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of the affayres in the ſeruice of God, your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and the Countrey.</p>
            <p>Béeing moſt ſorie that God hath not endued me with<note n="11" place="margin">Certainly you haue great cauſe to be ſory therfore. For you haue great neede of the ſame, leaſt you be beguyled by the Spaniardes, who will mocke you as they haue done others, as is to be ſéene by the example of the priſoners euen to the moſt ſimple Gentlemen of theſe Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treyes, of the which they redeeme not one. But as for the Italia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and Albanoys, which are better for the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards, they leaue them not in priſon.</note> greater ſence and experience, that I might be more able and fytte, to exerciſe the ſame charge with greater woorthineſſe. Neuertheleſſe, I wyll ſpare neyther paynes nor trauayle, to attayne to the premiſſes. And would not for all that, wyllingly giue place to any other whatſoeuer he were, that he could truly vaunt, that he would more<note n="12" place="margin">Thy actions paſt, giue good witneſſe of thy fidelity, the belly of thy playnes, and the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ocke of thy frankenes.</note> franckly, faithfully, and plainly, employe him ſelfe in the ſame then I: Although I vnderſtand that certayne perſons.<note n="13" place="margin">To wit the Abbot of Hannon with his train, according to the nature of the Monks, which do alwayes grunt one againſt an other, as a droue of Hogs.</note> Ielous of my good lucke, and enemies of my proſperitie, would haue impugned the ſayde denomination, and my Lord the Prelate of Saint <hi>Gertrudes,</hi> ſyniſterly quarrelling, and interpreting our actions paſſed. Wherin they ſhew them ſelues<note n="14" place="margin">Then it is a ſigne that what thou haſt don heretofore, hath bene but fayning and treaſon.</note> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduiſed, and too full of paſſions: for as much as all that we dyd, was by theyr expreſſe charge. It béeing verie vnſéemely for them, that they would<note n="15" place="margin">See how theſe hogs can one no more then an other, clenſe them ſelues of their filthyneſſe.</note> cléere them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, to caſt the fault vpon others: Conſidering that by the rule of equitie, no man is to be receyued to accuſe an other, him ſelfe béeing guilty of the ſame matter. And for that by the<note n="16" place="margin">
                  <p>He confeſſeth himſelf with the reſt, to haue ben faulty, and to haue ſtood in neede of grace.</p>
                  <p>Mounſier the Monke ſayth wel, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he repenteth of his offences. But he will receyue no diſciplin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and mainteyneth that there is great reward due vnto him for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good ſeruices that he hath done. So ſhameles and impudent he is.</p>
               </note> clemency of your Maieſtie, all matters paſte are forgotten, it is impertinent to enter into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencion, vpbrayding, or any ſifting with vs, which were but theyr aſſociates. Otherwiſe, if there ſhould queſtion
<pb facs="tcp:176474:7"/> be had for the narrow examination of theyr behauiours: and all be interpreted to the worſt, they would not be found cléere. For if we haue done amyſſe, they haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded vs otherwiſe then they ought to haue done.</p>
            <p>It were beſt to ſet all theſe reproches aſyde, and to ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in good ſadneſſe, howe to ſette vp that which is fallen downe, and procure by good vnanimytie, and mutuall aſſiſtaunce, the redreſſing of matters, in acknowledging our God, our King, and our Lawe. Which for mine owne parte I am determyned to doo, maynteyning my ſelfe in that<note n="17" place="margin">My Lord Abbot wil forget neyther his ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor couetouſneſſe.</note> degrée of honour, wherein it hath pleaſed your Maieſtie to place me. For that I will neyther yéeld nor giue place vnto them: for they haue no occaſion to be at debate with me. Sauing for that I would not agrée to their perticular appoyntment, hauing iudged it too burdenſome, and<note n="18" place="margin">He betrayeth his companions, accuſing them to the Spaniards.</note> diſaduantagious to your Maieſtie. And that the fruite by them promiſed, would not come thereof. But that it were better to take payne, to come to a generall Peace. And I thinke that I haue not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by deſerued to be<note n="19" place="margin">This Monke wyll become a ſouldiour, or peraduenture he feareth to be turned out of his frocke, as he hath bene put beſide the myter of S. Bartin: for theſe be the Armes he ſpeaketh of, and his honor is to be firſt ſet at the table and counſell, and to haue the Kitchen well furniſhed and the Kettell full.</note> diſgraded of Armes and Honour.</p>
            <p>For your Maieſtie may nowe eaſily ſée, and the euentes wyll more plainly declare, what is to be hoped thereby, and what foundation may be layde with perſonnages, which<note n="20" place="margin">See here how theſe good ſeruaunts of the King agree together, &amp; what the Townes of Haynault &amp; Artoys ought to expect at the handes of ſo good proc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of their owne cauſe, ſeeing that without any lymitation or reſtraynt, they meane to put them in ſubiection to the yoke of the Spaniards, with the prize y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Abbots, may ſaue their goods and credite with the king. Note alſo, how the peace of Artoys will be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted by the Spany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardes, ſeeing their owne Abbots make ſo goodly gloſes vpon the ſome.</note> lymitte the aucthoritie of the ſame, after their owne diſcretion: and wyll be ſéeking rather to aduaunce theyr perticular affayres, then to mayntayne eyther the Catholique<note n="21" place="margin">Vniuerſall perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar.</note> Romiſhe Religion, or the aucthoritie of your Maieſtie. And that if matter fall not out accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their pleaſures: they might drawe men to wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe at euerie howre (the examples are already at the gate,) in doing more diſſeruiſe in a day: then all this appoyntment would bring profite to the ſame in a whole yéere.</p>
            <p>And becauſe ſome of them knowe, that I wyll<note n="22" place="margin">He will be ſtyll vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull to his owne, to get the good will of the Spanyardes.</note> hyde nothing, and knowe theyr deſartes, and valours well inough, they loue not to haue me admytted into the ſayd Counſell: Meaning them ſelues, to gouerne euery
<pb facs="tcp:176474:8"/> thing after theyr owne faſhion. Your Maieſtie wyll ordayne in that behalfe, as by his prouident diſcretion, the ſame ſhall Iudge moſt conuenient, for his better ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice.</p>
            <p>Expecting the commaundement of the ſame, I wyll goe into <hi>Haynault,</hi> to my Lorde, the Prince of <hi>Parma,</hi> ſo ſoone as my Lord the Duke of <hi>Arſchotte</hi> may depart from <hi>Aixe,</hi> after my Lady his Wife ſhall recouer her health, to diſpoſe my ſelfe, according to his commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement. And to ſet my ſelfe in actuall ſeruice, as well to preſerue the aucthoritie of your Maieſtie (which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, bothe nowe and hereafter, might receaue great diminution and hurt:) As to ſaue mine honour. For otherwiſe, I might be declared<note n="23" place="margin">Thou art infamous enough, without other declaration.</note> infamous, and vnworthy to receyue any benefite of your Maieſtie.<note n="24" place="margin">
                  <p>To wyt. In caſe we haue nothing to aſſwage his ambition and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe. He had rather become a Chaplen and bondman.</p>
                  <p>Note the great humy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of this good Monk.</p>
               </note> Were it not for that, I would deſire nothing more then that I might retyre into my<note n="25" place="margin">Thou ſhouldeſt haue bene there, to haue bene lead to Boncham, with the Lord of Selles.</note> lyttle Monaſtery of <hi>Marolles,</hi> to my Cobrethren, to ſerue God in reſt of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and minde: béeing ſequeſtred and delyuered from all publyque affayres.</p>
            <p>Herevppon I wyll praye the Creatour, to graunt your Maieſtie, in proſperitie and health, a long and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py lyfe: Kyſſing the handes of the ſame, in ſaluting the good graces thereof, with my moſt humble recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From <hi>Cullen</hi> 
                  <date>the .xxv. of Iune. <hi>1580.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline> 
               <hi>Vnder vvas vvritten in this manner.</hi>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Maieſties moſt humble and moſt obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient ſeruaunt and Oratour. Sygned.</hi> Fredericke <hi>Abbot of</hi> Marolles.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſuperſcription was thus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To the King.</hi>
               </p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:176474:8"/>
            <head>¶ The tranſlation of the Letters of Iaſper Schets, <hi>Lord of</hi> Grobbendonk: Written in Latin to the Preſident <hi>Fonck.</hi> The fowrth Letter.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Will not declare in woordes,</hi> (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit I might very well) the ſinguler ioye that I receyued, when I vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode that your Lordſhip had ſo proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous ſayling from Fraunce, that the ſame arriued within thrée dayes at the Porte of <hi>Larede</hi> in Spayne, referring the iudgement thereof vnto you,<note n="1" place="margin">Note the great freendſhip of theſe good men. For according to the olde prouerbe: Lyke wyll to lyke.</note> according to the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall fréendſhip that is betwéene vs. But it lyketh me very well, to imagin that the moſt honorable Cardinall your Patron, hath not onely very courteouſly: But alſo with gratulation receyued you. Séeing that by his laſt Letters to me written, he ſignified vnto me, that with a feruent deſyre he had long looked for you, in hope that you would vnburden, and diſcharge him of ſome parte of his labours: admoniſhing me alſo, that the care of my buſineſſe ſhould be committed vnto you: Then the which nothing more ioyfull or acceptable, could be brought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me for newes. For I haue ſet all my hope in your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuolence onely.</p>
            <p>It remayneth now, that your Lordſhip ſhew your ſelfe vnto me in effect the ſame, that you haue ſtedfaſtly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to me. Ye haue alſo my Supplication<note n="2" place="margin">To wyt, to demaund money.</note> that I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered vnto you at your departing: you haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Articles of my peticions. I thinke you yet reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber ſome of thoſe thinges which I declared vnto you by woord of mouth. Therfore I thought it not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient to be tedious vnto you, with any long repiticion of the ſame matters. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit I thought it not altogether ſuperfluous, bréefly to admoniſh you of it by the way, to the end that you ſhould not forgette me.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176474:9"/>
            <p>I thinke alſo that the Duke<note n="3" place="margin">As long then as the Duke of Terra Noua, was at Cullen, the faythfull Schetz, who was Deputy to the States, ſollicited his owne affayres, yea, with their moſt great enimy, and ſtudied to betray the States.</note> of <hi>Terra Noua</hi> wyll be preſent, who hath very lyberally promiſed me his fauor, as well in his abſence by Letters: as in preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce by woord of mouth. And certainly he may in this behalfe, by his interceſſion, helpe and aduaunce, the good affection that you beare vnto me, and make the ſame more effectuall and of greater efficacie. I holde my ſelfe aſſured that you who are ſuch excellent Patrones, not onely for the affection which you beare me, but alſo by the aucthority that you haue with the King: wyll helpe and aſſyſt mée your Client, altogether depreſſed and brought lowe by the generall iniuries of the tyme, and the particuler ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of mine enemies: to the ende, that at the leaſt, béeing diſcharged of my debtes, which I haue runne and entred into, not by reaſon of my accoumpts, or particuler neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities: But by doing my ready ſeruice in all thinges to the<note n="4" place="margin">At the ſame tyme that being here, he falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fayned &amp; diſſembled whatſoeuer they would wiſhe at his handes.</note> King: I might héereafter prouide for my chyldren that they fall not into extremity, and ſo with a ſetled &amp; quiet minde, conſecrate the reſt of my lyfe vnto<note n="5" place="margin">To wit, to Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne and Mercurie, as he is accuſtomed. For the good man careth not whether God be hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or not.</note> God: or if it ſhall pleaſe his Maieſtie to employ me in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: that then I might more promptly and chéerefully, (ſo farre as my age wyll ſuffer) execute the duty of my office.</p>
            <p>But that can not be effected, except his Maieſty giue earneſt and ſtraight commaundement, that I may be payde without delay, whatſoeuer ſhall appeare vpon the due rendring of my accoumpts, to be due vnto me. The which howe it may moſt conueniently be accompliſhed: I thinke I haue ſet downe in my ſayde Supplication.</p>
            <p>Others that haue ſerued the King a long tyme, waxing ritch, accuſtome to be carefull, and procure that they may be honoured and encreaſed, with tytles of honour and great benefites,<note n="7" place="margin">Yet ſo it is, that being not content with thy fortune, how proſperous ſo euer it were: Thou haſt by Vſurie aſpyred to gouerne the Kings Coffers.</note> ſeruing as it were for recompences and thankſgiuing for theyr rewardes. But as for <hi>6.</hi> me, I haue reaped thus much of all my continuall ſeruice for thyrtie yéeres, or thereabouts, that I finde that I haue not loſt my goodes onely, but mine honour alſo.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176474:9"/>
            <p>Certainly, I féele at this preſent more want of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, then euer before. By reaſon of my harde Fortune, and my Creditors perceyuing it, I finde them more ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous and haſty with me, then they were wont to be.</p>
            <p>For which cauſe, I will eſtéeme it as a gratious good turne: if that which vppon the iuſt caſting vp of my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coumpts, is manifeſtly found to be due vnto me, be payd to my handes, or at the very leaſt, that the debt may be aſſygned with ſuch aſſuraunce, that with all by this ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient caution my Creditors béeing pacified, may ceaſe from troubling me. Yet notwithſtanding, I ſollycite not this with ſuch ſcrupuloſitie that I would, make any diffycultie to receyue, or neglect any good<note n="7" place="margin">For couetouſneſſe is vnſatiable.</note> benefice which might be offered vnto me by ſo great and mighty a Prince. But for that I deſire principally before all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinges, to be releaſed and fréeed from this trouble and tediouſneſſe. Wherefore at the laſt I ſhall deſire your Lordſhippe to procure me to be enrolled amongſt them that haue deſerued to taſte of the kings beneficence and lyberallytie, when occaſion ſhall ſerue thereto.</p>
            <p>But my chéefe deſire is that the ſame may be beſtowed vpon my chyldren, whome I haue of purpoſe cauſed to be trayned vp in ſuch inſtructions and learning, that they ſhould growe to be apt and fitte to ſerue, as well Royall and publique affayres, as alſo Eccleſiaſticall dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities. Some of them there be, that I haue deſtined &amp; appointed to the<note n="8" place="margin">To wyt, to tranſferre to their owne vſes great Reuenues, pertayning to the poore. For this is the Religion of Spayn and the duty they doo to the Church.</note> Church, and which towardly frame them ſelues to adorne and aduaunce the ſame, as apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth. I haue others very fitte for any manner of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices whatſoeuer they be. All the which I recommend to your Lordſhip, as a principall fréend, to the ende that they may be further recommended.</p>
            <p>I will vſe no moe woords vnto you, referring all other matters to my Letters the laſt of March, the .v. of April, and the .xx. of May alſo: all the which I thinke were in Spayne before your Lordſhippe, wherein I then bréefly comprehended the courſe of all that hath paſſed héere,
<pb facs="tcp:176474:10"/> ſince your departing. The ayde ſo long ſollicited and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, is ſent to <hi>Groeninghen</hi> at laſt, &amp; that verily by the dilligence of our<note n="9" place="margin">He would ſay, Buffo, to wyt, a Toade, who vnder coulour of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadorſhyppe, hath wickedly ſpread his poyſon againſt his moſt innocent Countrey.</note> 
               <hi>Bucho,</hi> rather then by the ſollicita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the kings<note n="10" place="margin">What wyll the Prince of Parma ſay to that? Who careth not for any thing that may ayde the Countrey, ſo that hee procure the kingdome of Portugall for him and his?</note> counſayle of Eſtate. The ſayd <hi>Bucho</hi> hath ſo handled the matter, that eyther without any, or at the leaſt with a very ſmall expence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kings money. He hath cauſed a iuſt army to be leuyed, &amp; brought ouer the <hi>Rhyne,</hi> after that about ſixe hundred horſemen, ſent from the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> for ayde, were ioyned to the footemen, which had ſoiourned a good whyle about the ſame Ryuer, but onely putting them in hope to receyue two months pay héere. And albeit they be diſappoynted<note n="11" place="margin">Beholde the fayre promiſes, wherwith they haue hytherto fed the poore Malcontents.</note> therof, yet hauing paſſed the <hi>Rhyne</hi> with the reſt, they haue made haſte in marching together with ſuch dilly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, that hauing paſſed ouer all the riuers, where there was any daunger: It is thought y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be already ſafely entred into <hi>Frizeland.</hi> In déede there ran a rumor, that the Prince of <hi>Orenge</hi> would giue them impediment: but beſides rumors, nothing elſe is yet<note n="12" place="margin">Count not your Chickens before they be hatched.</note> heard of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sauing that certayne Shyps of warre, which peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture were ſent to that effect &amp; came too late, preſented them ſelues before this Towne. The which after they had ſtayed héere a certayne tyme, hauing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement to depart: it is vncertaine whether they haue ſayled. In the meane ſpace we hope y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the iſſue of the expedition will be proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, taking this for a good preſage, that the <hi>Frizelanders</hi> at the onely report of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, began to be more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue &amp; carefull how to run away: then to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to theyr defence. Further, they of <hi>Groeninghen,</hi> ſince the death of <hi>Bartholomew Ente,</hi> ſlayne in an excurſion, who was in a manner the principall leader of the enimies, haue taken courage. Your Lordſhip very well knowing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcituation and importance of that Countrey, vnderſtanding aſwell with how great hope ſuch as beare good affection to his Maieſty, doo now reioyce. Who by reaſon of <hi>Dieſt,</hi> lately occupied againe by the Statesmen; are tormented with a new doubtfulnes &amp; feare, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they perceyue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Louain</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:176474:10"/> therby ſtandeth in emynent &amp; preſent daunger, with all the Countrey of <hi>Brabant:</hi> which the Prince of <hi>Orenge</hi> would haue had ere this, if <hi>Bolſeduke</hi> had not giuen im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment thereto. The report goeth, that the Abbot of S. <hi>Gertrude,</hi> with his preſence, maynteyneth &amp; kéepeth the men of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Towne in theyr dutyes: who I think is not exempt from feare, whyle he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidereth with him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe, that all the Kings men by ſuch newes of the taking of Townes, loſe courage, &amp; waxe faynt, for<note n="13" place="margin">Behold the prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and monſtrous rytches, whereby they promiſed to defend them ſelues, without the charging of the inhab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunts of Artoys and Haynault.</note> great ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of money. For want of money, giueth pretence to neglygence &amp; wicked dealing, &amp; turneth from the wayes of dutifulneſſe, the mindes of all ſuch as remayne in ſo doubtfull an eſtate: I knowe too well, that the warre of <hi>Portugall</hi> conſumeth the Treaſure &amp; Reuenues, and that it is not poſſible for them to furniſhe all neceſſities.<note n="14" place="margin">Schetz, hath in all reſpects, a Spaniſhe minde: to wyt, ſwelling and proude For that he thinketh th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ſo floriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a kingdome may be ſo eaſily ouercome.</note> But I am of this opinion, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it were expedient to take ſome order in it quickly, or that it had bene better neuer to haue bene<note n="15" place="margin">For the warre ought not to be tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſly moued, &amp; againſt the priueledges of Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugall, by the enemy the Spanyard.</note> enterpryſed. The euent of this warre is of great importaunce, for our affayres in theſe quarters. Wherfore I beſéech your Lordſhyp, that the ſame would vouchſafe to wryte vnto me howe the matter ſtandeth, concerning the ſame warre. And if after the ende therof, there ſhould be want of corage, or meane to atchieue our matters in good order: I feare y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſhall one day ſée thoſe thinges ſet foorth too late, which in fytte and conuenient time to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude Peace, peraduenture haue bene too hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denyed. I will not deny, but that the exerciſe of diuers Religions is very vnconuenient, in a wel ordred co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth, as the moſt honorable Cardinall hath<note n="16" place="margin">But if thou ſpeakeſt from thy heart, thou thinkeſt thy Cardinall very vnwyſe for ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ſuch fooliſh counſel to his King.</note> wiſely admoniſhed me. But all men, ſpecially theſe that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt theſe troubles, are perſwaded that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing ought to be<note n="17" place="margin">To wyt, tyll they ſhall finde occaſion fytte to deſtroy vs.</note> tollerated ſomtimes, which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not<note n="18" place="margin">For they reſerue that which ſhould be conſumed afterward, for the hote yron.</note> immediatly be amended. And that it is requiſite to auoyd the greater inconuenientes, with ſuffering the leſſer, although that they which be far of, and no ſéeers of the euylles, but hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers onely: are not of the ſame opinion. To whome theſe woordes of the Comycall Poet, might fitly be obiected.
<pb facs="tcp:176474:11"/> 
               <hi>If thou vvere in my caſe, thou vvouldest be of an other minde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that I may make an ende, I beſéeche your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to procure that we fayle not in our dutyes, namely, to make Peace by what meanes ſo euer, or to make warre. Fearing leaſt we doo that too late, which ought to be effected in conuenient tyme. Of all auncientie, the houſe of <hi>Auſtriche</hi> hath bene blamed with this ſpotte, that it hath accuſtomed to apply remedy<note n="19" place="margin">But now they of Auſtriche, although it be very late, giue no remedy.</note> too late to the euilles therof. For the which cauſe it is expedient that your Lordſhip, by your counſayles preuent that the king ſtumble not againe at the ſame Rocke.</p>
            <p>At this preſent there is a treaty at <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> touching the renunciation of the King, and the accepting of <hi>Alan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon:</hi> but as farre as I heare, the voyces neyther condiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cende, nor agrée together in ſo wicked a cauſe.<note n="20" place="margin">Whether theſe deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners be true, the effect in the ende ſhall declare.</note> All men for the moſt part preſage that, by procuring the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuration of the King aforehand, the way is opened and prepared for the Prince of <hi>Orenge.</hi> Howſoeuer it be, theſe counſayles are daungerous, and the King ought to haue great regard to the ſame. We léeſe that is ours more lightly (although vniuſtly,) then we recouer the ſame (albeit iuſtly.) But héere I will ceaſe, hartily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending my ſelfe to your Lordſhippe, to the which God graunt proſperity. Dated at <hi>Cullen,</hi> the .xvi. of Iune. <hi>1580.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AFter I had writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this Letter,<note n="21" place="margin">Here it may be ſeene howe long the Abbot hath bene a Traytor.</note> the Abbot of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolles</hi> béeing by chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce then preſent, moued through my example, ſayd that he would alſo write to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. And therwithall hath cauſed me to remember, to recommend vnto you<note n="22" place="margin">The Abbot hath a principall care of this: To wyt, the good father is enflamed with the loue of the Church.</note> his matter, touching the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of S. <hi>Bertin.</hi> I thinke you haue in remembraunce as béeing in the ſame company, when we were here to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, that the ſame was promiſed vnto him. And that you are not ignoraunt how much good fayth is woorth.</p>
            <p>Therefore for as much as promiſe hath bene performed with him, touching the kinges denomination of him, to be in the counſell of Eſtate. It ſéemeth alſo to be very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient
<pb facs="tcp:176474:11"/> that the lyke were done co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning his Pencion. And therefore I recommend him to your Lordſhippe as much as is poſſible. Wiſhing to the ſame agayne good health and proſperity. The yéere place and day aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde. This is the copy of my laſt Letter written to your Lordſhippe, which I thought good to copy out and ſende, if perchaunce by the iniurie of the tyme, it might ſo fall out, that the Letters were intercepted.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From <hi>Cullen</hi> 
                  <date>the .xxvi. of Iune. <hi>1580.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Moſt affectionate to your Lordship, <hi>Iaſper Schetz.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer type="direction"> 
               <hi>To the reuerend and moſt honorable Lord, <hi>Iohn Fonke,</hi> Prouoſte of Saint <hi>Marie</hi> at <hi>Cullen,</hi> Counſayller to the Catholique Kinges Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie.</hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="letter">
            <head>¶ To the ſame Lord. The fifth Letter.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not poſsible for me (moſt honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> Lord Preſident (to expreſſe the deſire that I haue at this preſent, to receyue Letters from you, the which might in a manner ſet before me bothe commodities and inconueniencies, together with the congratulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your welcome to the Court. To this ende, that I might ſéeme as it were to talke with my fréend, as much as is poſſyble for one that is abſent. The which in theſe moſt myſerable troubles, might ſomewhat comfort a man that remayneth in perplexitie. For I haue not yet left this exyle of <hi>Cullen,</hi> becauſe I could not hytherto ſet my affayres in ſuch order as I might make them ſure,<note place="margin">The goods of Schetz haue bene the only cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of his diſſymulation.</note> from the confiſcation of the aduerſaryes, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding that
<pb facs="tcp:176474:12"/> I haue aſſayed all meanes poſſyble therevnto, my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes béeing alwayes hyndred by delayes, procéeding of the iniurie of the tyme. Where as many others ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſéeke theyr gaine, and in lyke manner ſtyrre &amp; mooue from day to day, one whyle, one thing, &amp; an other whyle an other thing.<note place="margin">It is to be lamented, that thou waſt not fallen before vppon a very hangman in deede. Who with a halter might haue ſtopped the way of all thy treaſons.</note>
            </p>
            <p>My executioner <hi>Flemming,</hi> hath ſhewed him ſelfe open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abroade agayne, who alwayes lying in wayte for my lyfe &amp; honour, at this preſent taking occaſion by the time is reported to vſe meruaylous practiſes againſt me, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that he may with better ſucceſſe, vſe his wyles and deceypts againſt me that am abſent, and haue euyll wyll there: and peraduenture he wyll obteyne what he lyſt at the handes of the Iudges that wiſh me all euyll.<note place="margin">What haue the Iudges more to do againſt a Traytor that confeſſeth his offence?</note> And if it fortune that he worke many dommages againſt me, at the leaſt: he ſhall delyuer me from this exyle, vnlooſing the fetters wherewith I am in this place deteyned.</p>
            <p>I expect good newes from your Lordſhyp, of the Kings beneuolence, and aunſwer touching my peticions, to the ende that at the very leaſt, béeing diſcharged of my debts: I maye more patiently ſuffer the reſt of the iniuries of fortune, and of my tormenter <hi>Flemming.</hi> I will no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger kéepe your Lordſhyppe occupied with my particuler callamyties, I will ſpeake of matters pertayning to the common wealth.<note place="margin">And this man who was ſent by the States to treate the Peace: played an honeſt mans part.</note> Touching the proſperous ſucceſſe in <hi>Frizeland:</hi> My Lord the Prouoſt <hi>Aytta</hi> wryteth it. To whome as I yéeld the office of wryting, ſo I attrybute vnto him the glory, &amp; dexteritie of that is done. Without all doubt he hath done a great <hi>2</hi> péece of worke: which your Lordſhyppe ſhould not forget.<note place="margin">
                  <p n="2">2. To wyt, a notable great Treaſon.</p>
                  <p>It is not yet tyme to ſing the triumphe, for the matter is not yet in any wiſe finiſhed.</p>
                  <p>A great prayſe of Culle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hath ſo many good Cittizens, and louers of equitie.</p>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>For he hath not atchéeued a woorke of ſo great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, without expences and peryll, to the great gréefe of all ſuch as fauour the aduerſarie. Of the which there is a great number in this Cittie, as your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe well knoweth. What profite wyll come there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to the Kinges men, the tyme wyll teache?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176474:12"/>
            <p>For if the Gouernours in <hi>Frizeland</hi> doo theyr dutyes,<note place="margin">Where are the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes of golde that you promiſed to the Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents?</note> and that we fall not wholly into contempt, through lacke of money: Many preſage, that a more happy procéeding of the warre wyll ſuccéede this victorie, and that in the ende,<note n="3" place="margin">Myſerable Prophets who might ſee by the former warres, vpon how frayle a foundation they are ſtayed.</note> 
               <hi>Hollande</hi> maye be brought in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection.</p>
            <p>But this ſcantneſſe of<note n="4" place="margin">Where are the Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons wherewith the Malcontents ſhould be ſtored?</note> money, dooth at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent preſſe vs in ſuch ſorte, that the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> Gouernour, as an ydle perſonne, ſitting at the Sterne, is dryuen to committe the Shyppe to the wyndes. So ſlowlie the warre goeth forewarde.</p>
            <p>And by meanes thereof, the mindes of ſuch as haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhewed them ſelues ſcant of a conſtaunt diſpoſition, are brought to wauer. As for example, the Lorde of <hi>Auſsi,</hi> is agayne reuolted to the States, I knowe not well other wiſe for what occaſion: leauing his wyfe at <hi>Aloſt,</hi> who fayning her ſelfe angrie with her Huſband, (as it is reported) went about to betray the Towne alſo to the States: the Lord <hi>de Heze,</hi> béeing of the ſame conſpiracie of the which ſhée is kept priſoner at <hi>Aloſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>de Heze,</hi> when the treaſon that he pretended<note n="1" place="margin">But the Marqueſſe and Montigny, accuſe de Heze, by their Letters written to the States of Haynault &amp; Arroys, that he would haue delyuered Caſſell to the Duke of Amon.</note> to execute againſt the Marqueſſe of <hi>Richbourghe</hi> was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, béeing apprehended by the ſame Marqueſſe was ſent priſoner to <hi>Mons</hi> in <hi>Haynault.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With whoſe captiuitie, many of the principall Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours of his Regiment, béeing moued, fledde to <hi>Tournay.</hi> The report goeth, that theſe were ſolliceted by the Duke of <hi>Alanſon,</hi> and ouercome by promiſes to attempt the enterpriſe, by the counſell of the Prince of <hi>Orenge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it is well knowen that he which kept a Garriſon in <hi>Caſſell</hi> a Towne of Flaunders, by the preferment of the Lord <hi>de Montigny,</hi> was of the ſame conſpiracie. Who therefore (as it is ſayde) was ſet vppon in the playne feelde, by certayne Cornets of Horſes ouercome, and<note n="2" place="margin">But the ſame man perceyuing your diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty and treaſon, hath ioyned him ſelfe to good men, and peraduenture ye ſhall feele him alyue one day,</note> kylled in fighting: and ſo <hi>Caſſell</hi> (which the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries thought they had holden already in theyr handes) was preſerued for the king.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176474:13"/>
            <p>Theſe newes wyll ſéeme very ſtraunge to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp, as well as to me. But I thinke it a matter of deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that <hi>Heze</hi> and<note n="3" place="margin">Behold the rewardes of thoſe that are reuolted to the enemies, who care not for the priſoners, according to the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh faſhion. The which is experimented, not onely by Elimes, but alſo by Egmont, the which onely cauſe ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently purgeth the ſayd be Iuſſi from cryme, in that he hath followed better counſayle.</note> 
               <hi>Elimes</hi> his Lieuetenaunt, receyue the ſalarie of theyr Actes. I thinke alſo your Lordſhyp hath ſtyll in remembraunce, that <hi>de Auſſi</hi> firſt brought the Prince of <hi>Orenges</hi> ſouldiours into Flaunders, all the whole Counſell béeing againſt it, and how he cléered his dooing with<note n="4" place="margin">But de Auſſi ſayes thou lyeſt.</note> falſe Letters. Such rewardes are méete for ſuch déedes. Amongſt the which<note n="5" place="margin">Let the Malcontents iudge hereby what they are to looke for.</note> 
               <hi>Freſin</hi> alſo for his vehemencie, wherwith he was at the firſt ſo hote againſt the king, is peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture taxed to haue wrought ſome thing. And I thinke no leſſe wyll one day befall to his brother <hi>Mounſier de Loynſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> who depriueth the King of <hi>Cambray.</hi> I am ſory onely for this, that the nobillytie of our nation, wyll be noted and accuſed of vnfaythful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in Spayne, and all other Countreyes, by reaſon of theſe Metamorphoſies.<note n="6" place="margin">He will beware of your treaſonn.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But it is expedient for your Lordſhyp to doo this duty to your Countrey, that the diſpoſitions of thoſe that haue bene the workers of theſe thinges may be noted and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, for feare leaſt the offence of ſuch manner of men, which are but a fewe and moſt lyght,<note place="margin">Countreymen, you ſee all hope of peace taken from you, except the Friers be kindled again and the Spaniſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition eſtabliſhed.</note> defyle not all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with infamy. Further, ſéeing we muſt haue warre, for that there remayneth no hope to conclude Peace, by ſuffering the exerciſe of a ſtraunge Religion, God graunt it may be ordered with leſſe coſt, and more profit then it hath bene hitherto. Which in my iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wyll be brought to paſſe, if there be as many ſouldiours enrolled as the money will ſuffiſe to pay, leaſt for want of payment troubles aryſe. Secondly, that Colonels &amp; Captayns be taken and choſen,<note place="margin">Ye ſee Countreymen, what manner of mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators of peace ye haue had: is not this as much as to commit the ſheepe to the woolfe?</note> with ſingular diſcretion, who are neyther raunſackers nor cowardes. We haue héere the Earle of <hi>Swartzenberg,</hi> whome your Lordſhyp knoweth. He ſéemeth vnto me worthy to be recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and preferred for his lyberallytie, magnanymitie, and honorable repreſentation of body, and houſehold go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, whereby he kéepeth all his retynew in theyr
<pb facs="tcp:176474:13"/> dutyes. Wherevnto is to be added his great kyndred that he hath in <hi>Germany,</hi> the acquaintaunce and fréend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe in a manner of all the Princes, without forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the experience that he hath gotten by the affayres, wherein he hath bene a dealer. Whome lately in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mylliar talke I found very ready, and inclyned to ſerue the King. Wherfore, thinking that he is able to doo more then <hi>Focre,</hi> now deceaſed, or <hi>Fraunſberghe</hi> at this preſent altogether weakened, &amp; without force,<note place="margin">Fraunſberghe and Pouluyller, haue gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> great glory at the hands of the Spaniſhed ſort. For that they haue quitted them ſelues ſo well in ſpoyling the lowe Countreyes.</note> or <hi>Poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiller</hi> regarding all thinges leſſe then money: I haue by his owne conſent declared his minde, to the moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Cardinall.</p>
            <p>And I can not refrayne my ſelfe from recommending the ſame matter vnto you, not ſo much in reſpect that the ſayde Earle is my fréende: as for that in my iudgement, it would greatly redound to the profite of his Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>I beſéeche your Lordſhippe, to obtayne me aunſwere in this behalfe, to the ende I may not kéepe the honourable mans minde long in ſuſpence. God graunt you the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauncement of your enterpriſes, to your contentment.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>A diew.</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <date>The feaſt of S. <hi>Iohn Baptist,</hi>
                  </date> at <hi>Cullen. <date>1580.</date>
                  </hi>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>¶ The ſayde Earle will kéepe a certayne matter, that he hath to treate with the Emperor, in ſuſpence. Vntyll he receyue aunſwer from the King. Therfore I beſéeche your Lordſhip to vrge the ſame.</p>
            </postscript>
            <signed>
               <hi>Affectionate, and ready to doo ſeruice to your Lordship. <hi>Iaſper Schetz.</hi>
               </hi>
            </signed>
            <trailer type="direction"> 
               <hi>To the reuerend and honourable Lord. <hi>Iohn Foncke, &amp;c.</hi>
               </hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:176474:14"/>
            <head>¶ Certayne other Copyes of Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Abbot of Marolles: To the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident <hi>Foncke.</hi> The ſixt Letter.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Lord, ſuppoſing that ye are already</hi> arryued in Spayne, I would not be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde with my duty, to congratulate your proſperous arryuall, &amp; to ſay the <hi>Proficiat,</hi> of the Eſtate that his Maieſty hath vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaued to honour you withall Beſéeching God it may be to his honour, <hi>Et ad multos annos.</hi>
               <note n="1" place="margin">The Abbot was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready a Traytor.</note> For performance of that I made vnto you, when ye departed hence, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſe you from tyme to tyme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtate of our affayres. Maye it pleaſe you to vnderſtand firſt of all, that ſince that tyme there hath not happened any great alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, either good or bad, ſauing that according to the vttermoſt of all worldly affayres,<note n="2" place="margin">But loſt a great deale more then they haue won: by wytneſſe of the good Townes we haue taken.</note> ſometimes his Maieſties men haue triumphed, and otherwhyles haue loſt:<note n="3" place="margin">Such as are good to maintayne the Spaniſh tyranny.</note> The good perſeuere to procure the reſtabliſhing of the affayres.</p>
            <p>But the neceſſity that they ſuffer through want of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, ſuffreth not that they can execute their good inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions.<note n="5" place="margin">Where is the treaſure of Peru, that they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed.</note> The wicked waxe obſtinate more and more, preparing themſelues with all furie, to offenſiue and de: fenſiue warre. And though they haue bene well gauled in Flau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders: and their principall Captaines, as the<note n="6" place="margin">Maiſter Monke, ye haue no cauſe to be ſo ioyfull. For in ſteede of one priſoner of ours, we haue three of yours.</note> Lord <hi>de La noue,</hi> and other taken priſoners. <hi>Nihil tamen ſunt mutati ab illis, ſed potius facti deteriores et<note n="7" place="margin">Better reſolued then that they will ſell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> theyr lybertie and Countrey, for the Spanyardes rewardes.</note> obstinatiores, tantum abest, vt cum piſcatore icti ſapiant, imò nunc ſeriò vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentur egiſſe de abnegando rege et transferendo imperium in<note n="8" place="margin">Note, that the Abbot counſelled this an infinit many of tymes, when the time ſerued not. But what elſe may be looked for at a Monks hands, that haue no other God but his belly.</note> Alanſonium: Sed, ni fallor, quidquid dicant aut pretexant, credo sterni Auriaco viam. Quod ſi fit, mutatio parua erit aut paene nulla, quia propter ipſorum dicere aut nominare, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill mutabitur in re.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176474:14"/>
            <p>I haue written mine opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in that matter to my Lord the Cardinall: And ſée to my great gréefe, that their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacie, wyll cauſe the whole ruine and deſtruction of our Countrey. And that this warre wyll be of long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynuaunce, with great charges, and ſmall profite. For the feates<note n="9" place="margin">The Monk ſpeaketh lyke a braue warrior, to mayntayne his fleſhpot.</note> of Armes muſt be better ordered to get the victorie, or more muſt be graunted for the concluſion of Peace.</p>
            <p>The men of <hi>Cambray, Tournay,</hi> and <hi>Bouchain,</hi> make warre according to theyr cuſtome, deſtroying the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, to the great diſpleaſure &amp; detryment of the<note n="10" place="margin">Who feele the ſmart of the folly of theyr Gouernours and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Magiſtrates.</note> poore people. The Prince of <hi>Eſpinoy</hi> hath accepted the office of Generall. <hi>Mounſier de Ainſy,</hi> and they of <hi>Cambray. <hi>Iurarunt in verba Alanſon.</hi>
               </hi> So<note n="11" place="margin">By your infidelitie and treaſon.</note> all goeth amyſſe.</p>
            <p>I beſéeche you my Lord to vouchſafe, by your wiſedome and diſcretion to enforme his Maieſtie: in what ſtate at this preſent, the affayres in theſe parties remayne, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting him to followe the healthſome wayes of myld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and clemencie,<note n="12" place="margin">As appeareth by the contynuance of the warres, he maketh with all extremitie againſt his owne ſubiectes.</note> which he hath heretofore taken, and inclyning him rather to Peace, then to warre. <hi>Nam adhuc grandis restat via, quia illud vere quadrat in eos quod ſole vulgo dici, vno ſalus victis nulla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſperare ſalutem.</hi> I think you were a good whyle, ere this aduertiſed of our loſſe of <hi>Malines.</hi> And alſo that the Towne of <hi>Dieſt</hi> was ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in theſe dayes.<note n="13" place="margin">Here he calleth vs ouercome, and before h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſayde, that they haue not yet got the match. So he ſingeth a triumphe before the victorie.</note> Which wyll fall out very euyll for the poore Towne of <hi>Louain.</hi> Theſe be<note n="14" place="margin">Euents of the warre nay, rather fruites of your folly, which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth this warre, vnder coulour of Peace.</note>, euents of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> warre: And tyll there be ſome meane found to eſtabliſh an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Peace, each partie muſt prepare him ſelfe to beate, and be beaten. Touching mine owne<note n="15" place="margin">Which my Lord Abbot preferreth before the common wealth.</note> particular af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres, I reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend them vnto you, as to him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knoweth my<note n="16" place="margin">Theſe ſeruices are ſecrete ſeruices, that by theyr right named are called Treaſon &amp; Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony, committed againſt his countrey, &amp; againſt three Princes, whoſe Almo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he hath bene one after an other.</note> ſeruices &amp; good wyll, hoping that by your meanes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which hath bene fréely<note n="17" place="margin">The Abbot, then whyle he named him ſelfe Ambaſſador to the States, had created with the enemies, being ouercom by ſuch promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as are aduantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his fleſhpotte.</note> promiſed me by the Duke of <hi>Terra Noua,</hi> ſhall be ratified vnto me by his Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>For a beginning whereof, I haue had ſome experience already, hauing receyued vnderſtanding within theſe few dayes, by Letters from my Lord the Prince of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> that his ſayde Maieſtie had vouchſaued, to name me
<pb facs="tcp:176474:15"/> one of his Counſell of Eſtate, (notwithſtanding, that there was a diffycultie rayſed, by ſome of mine aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of<note n="18" place="margin">The Abbot of Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, as honeſt a man as he of Marolles: So one Woolfe will cyte an other.</note> myne owne profeſſion, whome I eſtéeme lytle or nothing,) which bringeth me in hope, that in ſhort tyme ſhall be giuen vnto me, the aſſygnification of the Pencion of<note n="19" place="margin">
                  <p>See that all is done for money, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ordinarie trade of Monkes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Metuo danaos et dona ferentes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> thrée thouſand Duckattes, that the ſayde Lord the Duke promiſed me, for giuing ouer myne acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, touching the Abbay of Saint <hi>Bertin.</hi> Beſides the abſolute forſaking of the adminiſtration that I had by the charge &amp; ordenaunce of the generall Eſtates. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto I beſéech you to lay to your good helping hand.</p>
            <p>Which ſhall make mée héeafter<note n="20" place="margin">20. Note, that money maketh him wylling to ſerue the King ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that: <hi>Curio romana non querit oues ſine lana.</hi>
               </note> more wylling to procure the ſeruice of his Maieſtie and the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, and binde men to doo you all the ſeruice that is poſſyble for me. Héerewith my Lorde, I wyll ende this preſent Letter, with my moſt humble recommendations to your good grace. Beſéeching the Creatour, to graunt you a proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and long life.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From <hi>Cullen,</hi> 
                  <date>the .xvij. of Iune. <hi>1580.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline> 
               <hi>Vnder was written.</hi>
               <signed>Your Lordships obedient Oratour.</signed> Vnder ſigned.
<signed>
                  <hi>Fredericke</hi> Abbot of <hi>Marolles.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="letter">
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> An other. The ſeuenth Letter.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Lord, fearing leaſt my Letters were</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercepted by the way, I would not let ſlyp by this<note n="1" place="margin">It was not too ſure for thanks be to God by this meane the Roſepot was found out.</note> aſſured meane of my Lord of <hi>Grobben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donkes</hi> man, to ſend you a copy of my former Letters: wherby your Lordſhyp may ſée what was then paſſed in theſe quarters worthy of aduertiſement: and alſo to giue you to vnderſtand at this preſent, the ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge Metamorphoſies happened here ſithence, by the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie of Malcontents, who are become euill ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nered.
<pb facs="tcp:176474:15"/> I meane the<note n="2" place="margin">They haue ſeene with theyr eyes, in what a whyrle pyt, they were plundged by the falſe perſwaſions of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne Monkes.</note> Lords of <hi>Heze, de Auxi,</hi> and theyr aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates, as my Lord of <hi>Grobbendonck,</hi> hath writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at large vnto your Lordſhyppe. But the victorie myraculouſly happened within theſe few dayes to our men, againſt the Rebelles, and Earle of <hi>Hollach</hi> with his men, endeuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to ſtoppe the ſuccours of <hi>Groeninghen</hi> (that you had ſo<note n="3" place="margin">Flattery for the Malcontents of Frize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, complayne aboue all thinges that they had no helpe from them of the Counſell.</note> carefully and dillygently procured, whylſt you were in this Cittie) cauſeth the loſſe of theſe perſonages to be forgotten. Specially, for that the ſayd <hi>de Heze,</hi> &amp; certaine Captaines priſoners. And as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Lord <hi>Grobbendonk</hi> informed me, he aduertiſed your Lordſhyp of the ſame: wherevnto I referre my ſelfe. Beſéeching you to be a meane that his ſayd Maieſty by this occaſion, withdraw not his<note n="4" place="margin">He ſhould ſay, deceyuing.</note> mercifull hand, nor diſtruſt his good<note n="5" place="margin">As is this maiſter Monke, who in hope to become ritch, hath forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken but three or fowre tymes the Princes, to whome he was bounde by oath. And in the ende betrayed the States of his Countrey, beeing ſent as their Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour.</note> ſtedfaſt, and conſtant vaſſalles: who by good reaſon are moſt ſory for this fowle and vntollerable faulte. Further recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> publique, my ſmall particuler affayres. With thus much, my Lord I praye God graunt you a long &amp; happy life, with my moſt humble reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendations to your good Lordſhyps grace. I wryte at this preſent to his Maieſtie, what hath paſſed touching my denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in the Counſell of Eſtate. Béeing ſure that my Letters wyll come to your hands. I pray you vouchſafe to giue good interpretation to the ſame, and to ad of your owne thereto, what you thinke may ſerue to my inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion: which is no other, but to further the ſeruice of his Maieſtie, to ſaue his Aucthoritie, and my honour.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From <hi>Cullen,</hi> 
                  <date>this .xxv. of Iune. <hi>1580.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordshyps obedient Oratour, to doo you ſeruice. Sygned, <hi>Fredericke,</hi> Abbot of <hi>Marolles.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer type="direction"> 
               <hi>The ſuperſcription was.</hi>
               <lb/> 
               <hi>To my Lord, my Lord Fonck, Preſident in Spayne, of his Maieſties Counſell, for the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres of Flaunders, My good Lord.</hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:176474:16"/>
            <head>A Copy of the Letter of the Lord of Grobbendonck. To Cardinall Granuellan. The eyght Letter.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Lord, although I haue not preſently</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Letter of your moſt honorable Lordſhips to make aunſwer vnto. But my ſelfe, expect aunſwer to thoſe letters which I haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: Yet for all that, ſéeing a matter of importaunce of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred for the ſeruice of his Maieſtie, I could not ſtay my ſelfe from wryting. And therfore, wheras ſince my laſt Letter, I thought more narrowly vpon the contents of your Lordſhips laſt Letter,<note n="1" place="margin">We beleeue now, that no Prince can procure vs peace, vnleſſe it bee with the rooting out of the Religion. For the Cardinall beeing cheefe of the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell, knoweth the Kinges meaning well inough.</note> wherby y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame diſcourſeth vnto me the exerciſe of two ſundry Religions cannot be tollerated, where men pretend to haue vnitie and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilytie, referring your ſelfe to the<note n="2" place="margin">The aunſwer ſhould be ſeene proouing the contrarie.</note> declarations made in that reſpect, by the States of the Duchie of <hi>Burgundy.</hi> I was moued to ſaye vnto your Lordſhyp hereby, that I perceyue verie well by ſuch ſpeache, that his Maieſties meaning is, not to graunt any more in the cauſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, then hath bene already agréed vpon. And<note n="3" place="margin">It is very rightly concluded.</note> conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſéeing Peace can not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded, without a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther graunt that his Maieſtie muſt<note n="4" place="margin">Therefore we alſo muſt reſolue the lyke, &amp; ſeeke all meanes to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend our ſelues without ſpending any more time about treaties, full of deceypt.</note> reſolue to make warre, to<note n="5" place="margin">Note, how theſe good Miniſters preſuppoſe &amp; perſwade the King that his Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey is loſt from him, except he can roote out all thoſe of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and gouerne the Countrey with a club, and without any contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction or interceſſion of the States. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon the King is fully reſolued to the warre, without leauing vs any hope of Peace.</note> recouer his Countrey, which vnder pretence of the ſayde Religion they would take from him.</p>
            <p>Now, my Lord, calling to remembraunce how the ſayd warre hath bene ordered hytherto, with his Maieſties great charge, and ſmall profite, I am ſorie for it. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be a matter beſide my profeſſion, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, for as much as the ſame is of ſo great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce to the common good, or euill of all in generall: I could not diſcharge my ſelfe of the care therof. Therfore I thought it my dutie, to aduertiſe your moſt honorable Lordſhip, that mine opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, that heretofore they haue
<pb facs="tcp:176474:16"/> erred in two reſpects, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende that your Lordſhyp may remedy the ſame hereafter.<note n="6" place="margin">Then ſpeakeſt better then the Duke of Alua, who had three ſcore, and ten thouſand men, and could not ouercome Holland and Zeland.</note> To wyt, they haue leuied ſo many men, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they could not pay them: And that they haue taken Captains without good examination of their quallities &amp; ſufficiency. Wherof procéeded the diſorder &amp; deſtruction of all Milletary diſcipline: without y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which no good effect can be hoped for. Praying the ſame ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to vouchſafe to ground him ſelfe rather vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſmall Campe well payde: then vpon a great one not payde, ſo much y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rather.<note n="7" place="margin">To burne vs in a ſmall fyre.</note> 
               <hi>Quod bellum istud trahendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> potius, quàm ſubito conficiendum, fore timeatur.</hi> And as touching the Captaines, <hi>Vt bonus habeatur delectus.</hi> And in this reſpect I may not hyde from your moſt honourable Lordſhyp, that béeing the other day in company with the<note n="8" place="margin">He is one of them th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> would iudge our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie, as the Fere dooth the Chickens.</note> Earle of <hi>Swartzenberghe,</hi> Ambaſſadour to his Maieſtie, we fell in talke of this matter ſo farre, that he complained vpon and lamented the ſmall ſeruice that his Maieſtie had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued of the men of his Nation, with ſo great charges,<note n="9" place="margin">They ſhall ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he will doo any better then the reſt.</note> Taxing with all the ſlackneſſe and couetouſneſſe of the heades and Colonelles, ſhewing him ſelfe verie ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, that the <hi>Germaine</hi> Nation, was in a manner defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med thereby.</p>
            <p>Wherevnto I made him aunſwere, that he was to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy the ſame as much as laye in him. And if his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie fell into the neceſſitie of this warre, then to ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde him ſelfe to the féelde, and to offer his ſeruice, ſo much the more, becauſe the iuſtification of the cauſe was knowen to him.<note n="10" place="margin">As with the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary partie and enemie, and not as an equall Arby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trator: to wyt, ſuch a one as his honour and promiſes commaunded him to be.</note> As hauing dealt in it with the other Princes. And that for ſuch he ought to helpe to defend it, and employ him ſelfe to reſtore vnto his Nation, the auncient reputation, which ſéemed vnto me the duty of a perſonage of his calling.</p>
            <p>And after this talke was a whyle continued, at laſt he grewe to this reſolution, that he would be content to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into his Maieſties ſeruice, ſo that he knewe whether the ſame would be acceptable, and that he might haue a charge graunted him, méete for his calling.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176474:17"/>
            <p>Further, declaring vnto me that ſince the death of the Emperour <hi>Maximilian,</hi> he was not ſo farre bound to the Emperour that now is, but that it was lawfull for him to accept this ſeruice. And that albeit, he was ſollicited by the Emperor, and alſo by the Duke of <hi>Bauiere,</hi> as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing before this ſerued the deceaſed Duke his Father, he thought to pacifie them both, by meanes of the ſeruice of the King: And ſo to treate with the Emperour, that ſeruing the King, he ſhould neuertheleſſe remaine in his ſeruice,<note n="11" place="margin">As good and faithfull as he.</note> placing an other in his rowme, in his abſence. And thereof he earneſtly deſired to haue your moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Lordſhyp aduertiſed: But vpon confidence and promiſe to haue the matter kept ſecrete, in caſe his<note n="12" place="margin">For lyke an honeſt man he wyll haue two ſtringes to his bowe, according to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe: If God will not haue mee, the Diuell prayeth mee.</note> Maieſtie haue no néede of his ſeruice.</p>
            <p>Wherefore my Lord, for that it ſéemeth vnto me, that the ſayde Earle procéedeth with good zeale, I thought it meete to aduertiſe your Lordſhyppe very particularly of the ſame, in conſideration that his ſayd Maieſtie maye reape good ſeruice at his handes, in caſe the ſame be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned to make warre: For as much as he hath many good quallyties, requiſite in a chéefe Captayne of men of warre. As that he is well Allied and eſtéemed in <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> and knowen of all the Princes, hauing already dealt in the affayres. Béeing of good repreſentation,<note n="13" place="margin">And groſſe.</note> Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in many languages,<note n="14" place="margin">He meaneth, prodigall.</note> and very lyberall: wherby he ſhall haue meane, not onely to leuie men, but alſo to prouide better Officers &amp; Captaynes, and a good Lieue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunt, which is no ſmall matter in the warres. Your moſt honourable Lordſhip may thinke on it, &amp; propound the ſame, where and in ſuch ſort as you thinke good. In my ſimple iudgement it would be very good, to employe ſuch a one, rather then any other, for that his quallities ſerue not only for the exploytes of the warre, but alſo for counſell: and to haue in the Campe a perſonage, that with aucthority &amp; good ground, can ſpeake touching the iuſtification of the cauſe, béeing a thing of great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce in the warres, which Princes are conſtrained to
<pb facs="tcp:176474:17"/> make againſt their ſubiects. Referring the whole to your moſte honorable Lordſhippes wiſdome, onely beſéeching you moſte humble, to vouchſafe to pardon me, if I haue gone too farre in a matter that is without the compaſſe of my profeſſion, and that you would at your leaſure ſend me ſome aunſwer therunto, that according to the ſame I may order my ſelfe and frame my ſpeache to the ſayd Earle. Without ſaying any more hereby to your honorable Lordſhip, for that this Letter ſéemeth vnto me to be already too longe. I beſéeche our Lord to graunt you my Lorde, long and proſperous life in health.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From <hi>Cullen</hi> 
                  <date>this xxvi. of <hi>Iune. 1580.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
 Thus vnder ſigned.
<signed>Your moſte honorable and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Lordships moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſeruaunt. <hi>Iaſper Schetz.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>My Lorde <hi>Fonck</hi> will giue your Lordſhip part of the good newes of the ſuccors ſent from this Citie to them of <hi>Groeninghen,</hi> by meanes whereof it ſéemeth that<note n="15" place="margin">We hope it ſhall not ſo prooue.</note> all <hi>Friezland</hi> alreadie loſte may be recouered.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="letter">
            <head>¶ A Copie of a Letter of the Lorde Wormes, to the Lord De Gommicourt, Gouernour of <hi>Maſtreighte.</hi> The ninthe Letter.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Lord Gouernor I humbly recommend</hi> me to your good grace. This ſhalbe to aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe you, that I haue béene with my Lord the Earle of <hi>Manſfeld.</hi> He is in hand to fynde all meanes to content all the <hi>Allemains</hi> which are in the Countrey of <hi>Luxemburghe.</hi> For he hath charge from
<pb facs="tcp:176474:18"/> the Princeſſe of <hi>Parma,</hi> by all meanes in the world to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grée with them. My ſelfe haue béene with the Princeſſe. She tolde me that it is aboue a moneth ſince ſhe ſent, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well to the Kinge her Maiſter: as to all Princes in the world that are his fréendes, to fynde Money<note n="1" place="margin">Then ſhee hath not yet all thoſe Millions that the Malcontents ſo much bragged of.</note> the which mée thinkes, ſhe cannot accompliſh, as ſhe deſireth. Not withſtanding the woords of the ſayde Princeſſe, and the promiſes of the Earle of <hi>Manſfeeld:</hi> Our Regiment and <hi>Foncres</hi> menne, will not be content without they haue eight Monethes paie altogether, there are but thrée offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto them. I thinke that the ſayd Princeſſe being at accord with vs, will ſend vs to the ayde of the Friſelan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in default that nothing can be executed touchinge<note n="2" place="margin">Note that there be yet ſome of the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed ſorte in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey that are the cauſe of our erre ſolutions, a wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting occaſion to playe their parte.</note> the intelling that my Lord Gouernour wotteth of. I haue ſhewed your letter to my Lady the Princeſſe, who thinketh it very ſtraunge that the noble party of Gelder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land hath writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothing to vs ſince. Howbeit touching the other Perſonage. My Lady taketh him for an honeſt man, in aſſuraunce that for money all will goe well, though it be with leapes. When I departed from my Lady, ſhée gaue me one thing in commaundement, and not to me alone, but alſo to you and Captaine <hi>De Carpe,</hi> commaunding mée alſo to ſpeake therof to<note n="3" place="margin">This is one of the Arbitrators of peace, Grand Criado to the Pope.</note> the Elector of <hi>Cullen.</hi> He hath promiſed me to ſtand my fréend to my Lady the Princeſſe in this matter, and in all that he can beſides in the worlde. The thing that my Lady demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, is that by our meanes, we ſhould fynde the meanes to practiſe by force of Armes, to take, browne, or burne the Veſſelles of our enemies, which are néere to <hi>Bonne.</hi> The ſayd Lady hath promiſed that if we can bring it to paſſe, ſhée will giue vs thrée thouſand Crownes of golde. For that my men are but euill Armed. I pray my Lord Gouernour to ward the accompliſhment thereof, to ſend me ſixe and thirtie Souldiers with Muſquets, and ſeaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or eight Pikemen, Then I will ſée with<note n="4" place="margin">The Councellors of the Spaniardes.</note> the Elector &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:176474:18"/> 
               <hi>Mounſier Lopez</hi> whether we can finde the meane to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it. My Lady hath moſte expreſſely commaunded me, that I ſhould tell you by woord of mouthe, and ſpare for no Money to kéepe touche with thoſe<note n="5" place="margin">Of the Countrey of Gelderland.</note> Noble men aboueſayd. And that his Grace of<note n="6" place="margin">It is a good Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, but he is a Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and beaten in a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Rome.</note> Liege for the effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thereof will furniſh you with the ſumme of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Florens, of fyue and twentie Patars a peece. For that I am not well at eaſe you ſhall holde me excuſed, in that I am conſtrayned to<note n="7" place="margin">Surely there is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> great hurt in that.</note> write vnto you, being very ſory that I could not come to you my ſelfe: Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtanding, if you haue any matter of ſecretnes: ye may tell it to this preſent bearer my good fréende. Beléeue mée there is great pouertie that my men are ſo euill Armed. It is a horrible matter that there can no Armor be got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten at <hi>Cullen</hi> nor <hi>Franckefort</hi> ſcate for any Money. If the affaires of <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">There be enow ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> let him.</note> and the French Kings brother goe forward, as the reporte goeth, it will goe euill for the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> our Maiſter. No more at this time, but that here I wyll end, praying God, my Lord Gouernor to graunt you a moſte perfect longe and happie life.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Andrenac</hi> 
                  <date>this ſecond of <hi>Iuly,</hi> the yeare foureſcore.</date>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your humble and obedient ſeruaunt. <hi>VVormes.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>I know not what to thinke of that Prieſt of <hi>Gelder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which kéepeth himſelfe with my Lorde <hi>Conwer</hi> at <hi>Cullen:</hi> He is an euill man, for I can by no meane get the Armor of him.</p>
            </postscript>
            <trailer type="direction">
               <hi>The ſuperſcription was.</hi>
               <lb/> 
               <hi>To my Lord, my Lorde of <hi>Gommicourte,</hi> Gouernour of <hi>Maſtreight</hi> for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, at <hi>Maſtreight.</hi>
               </hi>
            </trailer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
